<html>
    <entry id="archive">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Create and manage a copy of an object. This is stored with a version number appended to the
identifier.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="commands">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[A complete list of commands supported by this component.

Syntax:
/commands.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="id">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[You may set an identifier for use in the current session and this will
be used to reference any object.

See also: clear_id, get_id]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="decode">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Takes a string encoded in base 64 or base 32 and decodes it.

See also: encode]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="encode">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Takes a given string and encodes it into base 32 or 64 as per request.

See also: decode]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="deserialize">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Takes the stored XML version of the object and reads it into the current store.

See also: serialize]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="list_keys">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[A complete list of all keys supported by this component.

Syntax:
list_keys]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="serialize">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Takes the current object and creates and XML version of it. This may be stored in a file
or simply printed to the console.

See also: deserialize]]>
    </body>
    </entry>

    <entry id="copy">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Create a copy of an object, assigning it a new id.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="create">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Creates a new object in the store. You will then be prompted to fill in each attribute for the
object in turn.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="edit">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Edit the current object's serialized form in an external editor (usually vim or nano).
Exiting the editor updates the object.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="list_keys">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
List the keys for all the properties of this object.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ls">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
List the current object or other objects.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="change_id">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Change the id of the current object. Note that this should only be done with
very good reason.

See also: copy]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rm">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Either remove an object or remove a property from the current object.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="rs">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Result set management. This command allows for a variety of operations on result sets.

See also: results]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="results">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Results are static sets of output from a search that are named and may be
queried separately.
Creation and management
-----------------------
You create them in searches using the -rs name flag, e.g.

admins> search >admin_id -r .*caltech.* -rs ligo

would search (in the admins store) the property name admin_id for any entry including the string "calttech"
and stash the results in a result set named "ligo". You may now use the rs command
to navigate this result set. You may have as many result sets as you like.

You may also restrict the results to a subset of properties with the -attr flag.

admins> search >admin_id -attr [allow_qdl,name] -r .*caltech.* -rs qdl_check

would search on the admin_id and the result set would have the two properties
listed. Showing the result set then only has those.

admins>rs list foo
  foo: 56 entries,  fields=[allow_qdl, name]

admins> rs show [11,17] foo
    11. true  | Test admin client caltech-IGWN
    12. true  | Test admin client caltech/LIGO
    13. false | IGWN admin for VIRGO 1
    14. true  | IGWN admin for VIRGO 2
    15. true  | LIGO issuer UW Milwaukee
    16. true  | LIGO issuer UW Madison

shows the subset from index 11 in the list up to but not including index 17 (or
the end of the list, whichever comes first).

The -show flag also allows for displaying subsets but be warned that if you searched for
a subset of properties, then only those are available. You may restrict to a subset of those,
but cannot display properties you do not have.

Result sets as arguments
------------------------
Most commands allow you to specify a result set or subset as an argument. The basic syntax is
-rs name (-- | -range) (list | integer)
where name is the name and the range is either a single integer giving the index in the set or a
list of them. Be aware that some commands only accept a single object (e.g. changing and id, which
would give multiple objects the same id.)

Lists
-----
Lists are actually valid QDL, though are restricted to being un-nested. You could
therefore list the elements of a result set named X from 1 through 6 as

rs show -range [1;7] X

Negative indices are allowed, which reference element from the end of the set

rs show -range -1 X

references the last element of the set X.

Similarly you could do a mass update as

update >debug_on -value false -rs X

would set the debug_on flag to false for every element in X

Caveat: Result sets are static! This means that an update will update the stored
        objects that the result set references. If you alter the stored object(s)
        you will need to refresh your result set accordingly.
]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="search">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
Search the store, You may search on a given property and may do so in several
ways. Consult the online help for this, in particular the --ex (note the double
hyphen) option will print many examples.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>

    <entry id="size">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
The number of entries in the store.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="update">
    <body>
    <![CDATA[Command.
A wide-ranging command that allows you to update an entire object, prompting you for
each property, or update a specific property.]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="version">
    <body><![CDATA[The current version of OA4MP is 6.x-SNAPSHOT.]]></body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="index">
        <body><![CDATA[
index - Supports a set id (from set_id), the index from a listing, an explicit identifier,
or a result set. If present it is always
the last argument.
You may get an index by
1. using the set_id command to set it globally. The index is then optional.
2. Explicitly give the unique identifier.
3. You may use the name of a result set. You may also restrict the elements used (see below).
4. IF you have listed the entire contents with ls, you may give the numeric index of the object
How to specify the range of indices used in a result set.
( -range  | -- ) (integer | list | iterator)
Examples of ranges are: 5 (integer), [2,4,5] (a list), [2;7] integers from to through 6 inclusive.
Negative indices are allowed and mean to take from the end of the list, so
my_command -- -1  my_set
returns the last element in the result set name my_set.
Note that while you may specify arguments this way, result sets are static and operations will
be carried out on the actual stored object.

For operations on result sets proper, see --help for the rs command.
]]></body>
    </entry>

    <entry id="qdl_lists">
    <body><![CDATA[
Note on QDL lists,
All of the keys for the current store are put into QDL, assigning their name to the
value, so you do not need to quote those.
If there are lists, you may use arbitrary expressions. Now, since OA4MP needs a
way to find the end of such statments (a thorny general parsing problem), just mark
the end using the end of expression marker, ^^. E.g.

rs show -attr [  'client_' + 'id' , 'desc' + 'ription'  ] ^^ c842

would send the entire list to QDL. In such cases you are writing QDL which is often overkill.
However, in conjunction with run_qdl, you may have arbitrarily complex statements for lists.
Note that if you should terminate every list statement with ^^ if you do any.
For the vast majority of lists, just use simple syntax, E.g.
rs show -attr [client_id,description] c842]]>
    </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="set_id">
        <body><![CDATA[You may set the id for this store for every operation that requires one
using an index. This means that if your command is, say, serialize, the following are equivalent

Note that if you set this, it overrides any argument you may give it as the index.
Case 1: Direct
cli>serialize my:unique:id
(output)


Case 2: Set the working id for the store
cli>set_id my:unique:id
cli>serialize
(output)

See also: index, clear_id, get_id]]>
        </body>
    </entry>
    <entry id="clear_id">
        <body><![CDATA[clear_id - removes any current]]>
        </body>
    </entry>
</html>
<!-- Template
    <entry id="">
        <body><![CDATA[]]>
        </body>
    </entry>
-->